我在想
l was thinking Hmm?
我在想…
I was thinking...
你和我可以离开这里到拜亚去玩玩
you and I might go away to Baia.
就下次赶集日过后
Hmm? After next market day.
那里应该不错
It's supposed to be nice there
看那儿最近有很多人去… 这个主意倒挺好，可是…
and seeing how crowded it's been-  That's a lovely idea, but--
可是什么？
But what?
我不能扔下莱蒂一个人
I can't leave Lyde alone.
她需要我  她需要你
She needs me.  She needs you.
伊万德已经失踪两个月了
Evander's been missing for two months. Something bad has happened.
有不祥的事发生了  很有可能发生了不祥的事情
very likely something bad has happened.
很有可能他已经死了！
very likely he is dead!
波罗，起来！
Pullo, awake!
醒醒！马克·安东尼在等我们
Wake up! Mark Antony's waiting.
去死吧你，你他妈的猪！
Mump off and die, you pigfucker.
好了
Right.
噢，谢谢你，我的蜜糖
Aw, thank you, my honey.
你不应该跟奴隶说谢谢
You shouldn't thank slaves.
又没有坏处  有损军纪
No harm in it.  It's bad for discipline.
今天早上心情不错？
Happy again this morning?
那内奥比呢？
Niobe, then?
她怎么样？ 我搞不懂她
How's she going?  I don't understand her.
为了她妹妹那个该死的丈夫的事情大惊小怪的
All the hoo over her sister's damn husband.
女人，呵？也许她是…她是…
Women, eh? Maybe she's- she's--
她是什么？
She's what?
我不知道女人，唉？
I don't know. Women, eh?
强大的高卢副征服者
Mighty vice-conqueror of Gaul,
男女战神都为你的所做所为而骄傲
Mars and Bellona swell with pride at your doings.
而我说… 噢，我的神啊！你说的是些什么废话啊
And I say-  Oh, good Juno, what cac you speak.
你就说重点好不好？
Would you just get on with your point, man?
马上！大人，我…
Immediately, Your Honor. I--
政治评论家赛尔维利斯来了
Publius Servilius is here.
哦，好，这下可以打发走这些人了，你下去吧
Ah, good. That'll do for this crowd then. Off with you.
我  你给我下去
l-  No, off with you!
群马的主人，人民的护民官马克·安东尼
Master of Horse and People's Tribune Mark Antony
将于明天接待你们的请愿
will receive your petitions tomorrow.
乌瑞纳斯！
vorenus!
出去！
Out!
辛西娅
Cynthia,
梨子，亲爱的，嗯？
a pear, my love, hmm?
赛尔维利斯
Servilius,
我亲爱的老朋友
my dear old friend.
你好吗？ 很好，身体很好，我谢谢你
How are you?  Healthy healthy, I thank you.
恕我冒昧，我们以前见过吗？
Forgive me, have we met before?
我们没有吗？
Have we not?
不记得了
No idea.
我对待文官总是装成这样
I always pretend so with civilians.
这样样更象个搞政治的，对不对？
It's more politic, nay?
这位一定是你美丽的夫人了
And this must be your beautiful wife,
她的名字我一时想不起来了
whose name escapes me.
芭佩娅
Poppaea.
是一种花
A flower.
你请别介意这儿乱糟糟的
You'll excuse all the bustle.
我发现庞贝的装潢品位实在是单调
I found Pompey's taste in decor rather dull.
我喜欢多点颜色
I like a little more color.
正如你所说  我们相信你一定会把它弄的很漂亮的
As you say.  You shall make it lovely, we are sure.
原谅我要和你丈夫谈点公事了，好吗？
You'll forgive me if I talk business with your husband?
当然
Of course.
就当我不在这儿  这不可能
Pretend I am not here.  lmpossible,
不过我试试，现在…
but I shall try. Now then...
我相信你知道恺撒
I'm sure you're aware that Caesar
在希腊期间让我留在这里掌管所有的事情
has left me in charge whilst he is in Greece.
是啊，他可有好玩的了，去追庞贝那些人
Yes. Off having fun chastising Pompey et al.
留我在这里像个他妈的文官一样做些动嘴皮子，动笔的工作
Left me here to scribble and quibble like a damned civilian.
不过我下决心做到最好，
However, I am determined to make the most of it.
做个好的政治家，
I shall be a good politician,
虽然还不如杀了我
even if it kills me.
要么就是害得别人被杀
Or if it kills anyone else for that matter.
好像，你是
So you are, it seems,
留在罗马资格最老的元老院议员
the most senior senator left in Rome.
很荣幸，我是
I have that honor.
除此之外，还是庞贝一党的叛徒  什么！？
And a turnabout Pompeian to boot.  l--
正因为这样我认为
Which is why I thought
这么做可能很有意思
it could be amusing
那就是，我们让你来作今年的执政官
if we made you consul for this year.
执政官？
Consul?
这是最好… 请允许我把话说完
That's most kind--Allow me to finish speaking.
下次元老院开会时
When the Senate next meets,
有几项法律条款
there are a couple of legislative items
我希望能看到它们立即生效
I wish to see enacted immediately.
我相信你一定会乐意支持的
I am sure you will be happy to assist.
我…我… 第一项：
l- l-  ltem one:
元老院将批准明年
The Senate will ratify
选举恺撒为你的共同执政官
Caesar's election as your co-consul for the coming year.
可是不管怎样他是个独裁者啊
But he is dictator in any case.
还是说他是执政官比较好听，
It sounds so much better if he is consul.
更亲切，这条你听清了？
It's more amicable.  You got that?
我…我，是的  第二项：你要提议
l- I do. l- I have.  ltem two: You will propose
如下法律：
the following law:
即日起，在意大利每个省里
Forthwith, in every province of ltaly,
所有畜牧业和农业的从业者的三分之一
one third of all those employed at laboring with cattle or in agriculture
必需是自由人或是公民
must be freedmen or citizens.
我不明白
I don't understand.
有太多的奴隶了，你明白吗？他们做了所有的工作
Too many slaves, you see? They've taken all the work,
导致自由的平民反而失业
which causes unemployment amongst the free populace.
现在，我们需要为我们的公民制造更多就业机会
Now, we need to create more jobs for our citizens.
但这样会付出很高的代价啊
But it will be hugely expensive!
是会
Mmm. It will.
但只不过是对那些拥有所有土地的极少数的有钱人
But only to those few rich men who own all the land.
而他们也应该会很欣慰于自己
And they shall have the consolation
做了一件非比寻常的爱国壮举
of having done something eminently patriotic.
这似乎比较…
It seems rather...
极段了，至少是这样的
extreme to say the least.
甚至可以说是破坏性的了
Ruinous even.
你有可能是对的
You may well be right.
但老实说，我才不管到底是富人还是穷人
But frankly, I do not care whether it is the rich, poor,
还是他们两边都遭殃呢
or, indeed both that suffer.
恺撒希望制订这条法律
Caesar wishes this law to be made.
他是我的朋友，我就要这么订
He is my friend, I will have it made.
要是你愿意，我可以绕过元老院
If you prefer, I could always bypass the Senate,
集合一群人民
call an Assembly of the People
你可以跟他们议论
and you can put your arguments to them.
一个像你这样优秀的雄辩家说不定就能说服他们
A fine orator like yourself might just persuade them
证明恺撒是错的
that Caesar is wrong.
那就不需要了  好
That won't be necessary.  Good.
好
Good.
那就这样
That's it then.
我不知道说什么好  那就什么也别说
I don't know what to say.  Say nothing then.
这总是最好的
It's often best.
你肯定认识波斯卡吧，恺撒的傀儡
You know Posca of course, Caesar's creature?
他会负责所有的细节的
He'll take all the details.
芭佩娅
Poppaea...
我亲爱的，如果你的丈夫过世了…
my dove, if your husband should die...
来找我，我们结婚，如何？
come to me, we will marry, neh?
他还是遵守诺言的，对不对？
So, keeping their promises, isn't he?
什么？
What?
恺撒和马克·安东尼做的是有益于人民的事情
Caesar and Mark Antony, doing right by the people.
你曾为这个而担心，不是吗？
That was your worry, wasn't it?
怕恺撒不过是又一个暴君？
That Caesar'd turn out to be just another tyrant sort?
但是现在他和马克·安东尼
But here's him and Mark Antony
在为失业的人找工作
getting jobs for the unemployed.
这下你总不能抱怨什么了吧，你？
You can't complain about that now, can you?
他在议政的时候要个妓女和个侏儒在旁边陪着
He negotiates with a whore and a dwarf at his side.
你认为辛辛纳图斯和马略即使是格拉古
Think you Cincinnatus or Marius or even the Grachii
会这样自贬身份吗？ 谁？
would demean themselves so?  Who?
谁都知道，马克·安东尼做事，有他自己的怪风格
Mark Antony has his odd ways, there's no denying that.
我不回家，我要喝两杯
I'm not going home. I need a drink.
喝酒？你？ 我，喝酒，怎么了？
Drink? You?  l. Drink. What of it?
我不跟你吵
I'll not argue.
哎唷！ 对不起
Ouch!  Sorry.
你要冷静点  要我怎么冷静，这样都两个月了
You need to calm down.  How can I be calm? Two months of this.
你剪完了没有？ 你能不能坐着别动？
Aren't you done yet?  Will you sit still?
你这样一副苦脸可抓不住一个好看的新丈夫
Won't catch a pretty new husband with a sour face like that.
我不要一个新丈夫，我要卡瑞多
I don't want a new husband. I want Crito.
你不能还跟一个牲畜贩子结婚
You can't stay married to a drover,
如今你爸爸可是个高级武官
not now that your father's a prefect.
这样不合适  我告诉过她了
It wouldn't be right.  I told her.
他差的太远了，你运气好，幸亏还没付嫁妆
Far too low. Fortune blessed you, you haven't paid out dowry.
别着急，我们会给你找个好的
Don't worry, we'll find you someone nice,
有合适的身份地位  我什么都不想要
and proper status.  I don't want anyone!
你这样的年纪不能不结婚，这样不体面
You can't be unmarried. It wouldn't be decent at your age.
她说体面  你这是什么意思？
Decent she says.  What's that supposed to mean?
你知道是什么意思
You know what it means.
你给我把嘴巴闭上  不然怎么样？
You hold your tongue.  Or what?
你能怎么样？
What will you do?
没事的，甜心，没事的
It's all right, sweetie. It's all right.
有一阵，我还以为事情会好，但现在
I thought it was going well for a while, but now...
也许我应该揍她，你说呢？
Maybe I should beat her, do you think?
我不知道，只有坚持才会有效果
I don't know. That only works if you keep at it.
每天好好地抽她们一两顿
A good thrashing once or twice a day
直到听话为止
till they're docile.
不过这样，她们就不好看了
But then they don't look so good.
把她这样的美人打的伤痕累累可不好
Be a shame to mark up a beauty like her.
她是啊？
She is, eh?
她是个美人
She's a beauty.
她是的
She is that.
我给她奴隶，钱，所有的东西，可我得到什么？
I give her slaves, money, everything. What do I get?
什么也没有
Nothing, that's what.
这就是我得到的一屋子的哀怨声
I get a house full of wailing.
我妻子甚至不愿和我行房事
My wife won't even couple with me.
为什么？
Why not?
她说不行，因为她妹妹住在这里
Says she can't while her sister stays.
有她妹妹什么事？
What's her sister to do with it?
这有什么关系？
What difference should that make?
她怎么了？
What is wrong with her?
她有什么问题？
我做错什么了
What is wrong with me
要让这样对待我
that I'm served this way?
也许你该离开她
You should leave her, maybe,
既然她让你如此难过
seeing as she makes you so unhappy.
不！我不会离开她
No! I will not leave her.
我宁愿死也不愿离开她
I'd rather die than leave her.
没事了，小羊羔
It's all right, lamb.
会好起来的
It'll be all right.
我说，什么人
Who, I say,
面对我在这里列举的
faced with the overwhelming force
这些数字和论据的强大说服力
of the figures and the arguments I have here marshalled
还能不同意这一压倒性的结论？
could resist their overwhelming conclusion?
因此我请求你们
Therefore I ask you,
尊敬的参议员们
honored conscript fathers,
支持我，通过这项重要的和…
to support me in this important and...
和爱国主义的立法，它将…
patriotic legislation which will--
有人想对这一倡议提出反对意见吗？
Does anyone wish to speak against the motion?
没有反对意见，不用投票表决
No opposition voiced. No division required.
提议通过
Motion carried.
空的
Empty.
如果没有酒了，水就行了
If there's no wine, water will do.
谢谢你，我的小鸽子
Thank you, my dove.
莱蒂，你知道，我到处打听过了
So, Lyde, I was asking around, you know,
关于你的男人伊万德的下落
about your man there, Evander.
四处打听？
Asking around?
看看能不能帮你找到点线索
See if I could find out anything for you.
只有我才认识几个黑道上的人
Only, I know a few shady characters see?
那种人也许知道一个人失踪了到底是怎么回事
Types that might know what's what when a man's gone missing.
反正，他们告诉我说
Anyroad, they tell me
他惹上了点麻烦
that he got himself into some trouble
是跟河对面的一些希腊小混混
with some nasty Greek boys across the river.
他们说是赌债  赌博？
Gambling debts they say.  Gambling?
伊万德从不赌博
Evander never gambled.
当然，这样的事情
Well sure, it's the sort of thing
一个男人是不会跟他的妻子提起的，对不对？
a man keeps quiet around his wife, isn't it?
你的意思是？
What are you saying?
我很抱歉这么跟你说，但是看样子他是不会回来了
I'm sorry to say it, but it looks like he's not coming home.
看样子是死了
Dead, looks like.
你确定？
Are you sure?
他们是这么告诉我的，
So they tell me.
死了，被杀了
Dead. Killed.
这不是真的
It isn't true.
我的意见是
My advice,
最好忘记他
best forget about him.
最好继续过你自己的生活
Best get on with your life.
这不是真的
It isn't true.
这也不算太坏
It's not so bad.
你身边还有很多爱你的人
You've still got people that love you.
看看他们
Look to them, eh?
内奥比，你说是不是
Isn't that right Niobe?
她最好坚强活下去
Best she gets on with her life.
为了那些爱她的人
Best she looks to the people that love her.
忘记伊万德，忘记过去
Forget Evander. Forget the past.
好了，我走了
Well, I'm away.
得去喝两杯为这一整天提提神
Need a drop of wine to set me up for the day.
莱蒂，请别这样
Lyde, please don't.
我真难过，对不起
I'm so sorry. I'm sorry.
你抱歉？
You're sorry?
现在说抱歉太晚了，不是吗？
It's too late for sorry, isn't it?
你跟他上床的时候怎么不知道对不起？
You weren't sorry when you were fucking him, were you?
你那个时候不知道抱歉，我去你妈的抱歉
You weren't sorry then. I piss on your sorrow!
我不会，嘘  你
Shh!  I will not shh. You shh!
你是个贼，是个婊子，你偷走了我的丈夫
You're a thief and a whore and you stole my husband!
我什么也没偷，是他来找我的
I stole nothing! He came to me!
他来找我，我从来就没有爱过他，我爱我的丈夫
He came to me! I never loved him. I love my husband!
要是你…如果你是…
And if you'd done- if you'd been--
如果我怎么样？
If I had done what?
如果我能给他生个小孩，对不对？
If I had given him a child. Is that it?
对不起，请原谅我，请原谅我
I am sorry. Please forgive me. Please forgive me!
原谅我！ 我诅咒你，姐姐
Forgive me!  I curse you, sister.
以复仇女神的名义起誓，我诅咒你
By grace of the Furies, I curse you.
我会替你保守秘密
I'll keep your secret
看在孩子的份上
for the sake of the child,
但从今以后你…
but don't you ever...
你再也不要跟我说一句话
ever speak to me again.
小心
Be careful!
Ah!
精彩，精彩
Bravo. Bravo.
一点嗜血欲望很适合你，屋大维
A little blood lust suits you, Octavian.
他很英俊吧，是不是？
You look very handsome. Does he not?
是的  泰特斯·波罗是个好老师
He does.  Titus Pullo is a good teacher.
很遗憾恺撒不在这里
Well it's a pity Caesar isn't here.
不然他会立刻把你编入他的军队里
He'd put you on his staff immediately.
也许你该到希腊去加入他
Perhaps you should go and join him in Greece,
让你的剑沾点儿真正的庞贝的血
get some real Pompeian blood on your sword.
别说傻话了，母亲  为什么不？
Don't be silly, Mother.  Well why not?
要是我们不赶快，庞贝和卡托，还有那些傻瓜们
If we are not quick, Pompey and Cato and all those fools
在屋大维崭露头角之前就死掉了
will be dead before Octavian gets his chance to shine.
他还是个孩子  我不是
He's still a child.  I am not.
他不是，他现在是个实足的小男子汉了
He is not. He is quite the little man now.
我认为长大成人可不仅仅是会舞剑
I should think there's more to manhood than swordplay.
屋大维
Octavian,
你有没有和女子交欢过？ 母亲，你…
have you penetrated anyone yet?  Mother, please.
这是说你有过还是没有？ 还没有，不过…
Does that mean you have or haven't?  Haven't, but--
泰特斯·波罗，我不是交待过你办这件事吗？
Titus Pullo, didn't I tell you to sort that out?
我肯定我说过的
I'm sure I did.
我…对不起，夫人，我会负责办的
I- sorry, ma'am. I'll see to it.
这就去办
Do that.
别担心，亲爱的，这真没什么难的
Don't worry, darling. There's really nothing to it.
就好像是，只要你坐上了马鞍
Once you're in the saddle, as it were,
一切都来的自然了，对不对，波罗
it'll all come naturally. Isn't that right, Pullo?
是的，夫人
That's right ma'am.
我提醒你，不要你们那些臭当兵的找的那种母夜叉一样的人
And none of your sordid soldier's she-wolves, mind you.
要干净，漂亮的
Something clean and pretty.
是，干净，漂亮的  好
Clean and pretty it is.  Good.
我让玛茹拉给你做件外袍
I'll get Merula make you a toga. What else?
还有什么？ 也许你能安排他杀一个人？
Perhaps you can arrange he kill someone.
适当的时候，会的
that will happen in due course.
我们优利亚家的人总少不了敌人
We Julii always have the needful enemies.
保佑我的孩子健康
Health to my child.
为我的女儿
My daughter.
我想要个儿子，一个健康的男孩
I wish for a son, a healthy son.
我，呃… 那么，晚安
l, uh-  Good night, then.
晚安
Good night.
Husband.
丈夫
What's all this?
这是干什么？
我想如果我们有些独处的时间，你可能会喜欢
I thought it might please you if we had some time alone.
我把姑娘们和卢西尔斯送到克莱蕊莎那去了
I sent the girls and Lucius to Clarissa.
莱蒂呢？ 她到一个朋友家去了
And Lyde?  She's gone to a friend's.
请坐下  我已经吃过了
Please, sit down.  I've already eaten.
不过…
But--
我还可以再吃点
I can have some more.
对不起
Excuse me.
和我一起坐
Sit down with me.
没关系  真的，坐
That's all right.  Really, sit.
我一个人也吃不完这所有的东西
I can't finish all this on my own.
日期刚好…
The calendar is correct...
如果你今晚愿意要我的话
if you would like to have me tonight.
我愿意
I would.
我很愿意
I'd like that.
我亲爱的马克·安东尼
My dear Mark Antony,
希望你收到这封信时身体健康，
I hope this finds you in better health
这更胜于我对胜利的渴望
than my hopes for victory.
我追赶庞贝从希腊的这一头到那一头
I chased Pompey from one end of Greece to the other
而他完全拒绝于我开战
and he resolutely refused to fight.
我原认为这是他一贯的愚蠢作风
I thought this was his usual obtuseness,
可是这老家伙还不算那么糊涂
but the old man has some sense left in him yet.
他一边逃避开战
While avoiding battle,
同时从东部纠集了十个兵团的人马
he has gathered a good 10 legions from the east,
这就大大超过了我方的军队人数
and I find myself badly outnumbered.
现在猫冲着狗叫嚣
Now the cat barks at the dog,
庞贝掉转头来追我了
and Pompey is chasing me.
我可以以策略致胜他一时
I can outmaneuver him for a while,
但不能一世
but not forever.
我的人马既疲倦，粮草又不足
My men are tired and ill-supplied,
而且我们很快就不得不停下来，跟他开战
and we shall soon have to stand and fight.
我要你火速把13军团带过来
I ask you to bring the 13th here as speedily as you are able.
该死的！
Damnation.
宣军团来使吗？
Shall I summon the legion legates?
不，等等
No. Wait.
我得考虑一下
I must think on this.
这个真好看
This is lovely.
哦，这正是你的颜色
Oh.  Oh, it's just your coloring.
夸张了点，我喜欢简单的东西
A little loud. I'd prefer something plainer.
简单有什么好，这个我们要了
What's the point in plain? We shall take it.
戴这个看看…
But this one...
美极了，哦，美极了
Divine. Oh, divine.
安东尼会喜欢这个，他喜欢看我打扮成东方风格
Antony will love this. He likes me in Eastern styles.
两个一起多少钱？ 五千
How much for both?  5,000.
你不如去偷吧  那么四千五
You are a thief.  Four and a half then.
三千
Three.
这么多钱我们付得起吗？
Can we afford such expense?
照恺撒在希腊的情形看
Things as they are with Caesar in Greece,
我们不应该更谨慎些吗？
surely we should be more prudent?
一点都不用担心，我亲爱的
Don't worry about a thing my dear,
我早想好了
I'm thinking ahead.
泰特斯·波罗来了，少爷
Titus Pullo is here, dominus.
哦，告诉他我不舒服
Oh. Tell him I am unwell.
要么让他下个星期再来
He may come back next week perhaps.
别跟他说这些
Tell him nothing of the sort.
告诉他，屋大维过一会就见他
Octavian will be ready to see him in one moment.
再给他一袋钱
And give him a purse.
亲爱的，你已经拖得够久的了
You've put off this moment long enough, my dear.
母亲
Mother--
你今天必须去找个女孩子交欢
You will penetrate someone today or I will
不然我就把你的破书都烧了
burn your wretched books in the yard.
你下去吧
Off with you.
借过，有贵族过来了，让路
Coming through. Noble coming through. Make way there.
别担心，少爷，这不算什么的
Don't worry, young master. There's nothing to it.
要是没什么，为什么搞得这么大惊小怪的？
If there is nothing to it, why is such a fuss made of the thing?
你很快就知道了
You'll soon find out.
去，去，你给我出去！
vai, vai! Be off with you!
这儿可不是兵团的妓寨，谢谢，请走
This isn't no infantry fuckhole, thank you very much.
不，甜心，别动肝火
Now now, my honey, calm your stomach.
我们来是为了这位年轻的少爷
We've come for the young master here.
我们有的是钱
Andwe'rewell coind.
哦，好吧，请你一定别介意
Oh well, excuse me, of course.
我不是故意无礼的
I meant no disrespect.
我们很荣幸为你效劳，少爷
We're honored to service you, young master.
年轻的少爷喜欢什么样的呢？
And what would be the young master's pleasure?
他是第一次，找个好点的
First timer. Nothing too savory.
我保证我们有你中意的
I'm sure we have just the thing.
一点异国情调，如何？
Something exotic, perhaps?
要么年轻点的？
Or else something young?
清秀，天真
Light, simple.
太瘦了点，是不是？
Little bit skinny, isn't it?
完了他都不会有感觉，是不是？
Won't know he's been, will he?
你都不会有感觉的
Won't know you've been.
这个丰满些
More substance,
可仍是个美少女
yet still nymphlike,
很优雅
graceful.
这个是刚从船上运到的…
This one's fresh off the boat...
就那个吧  慢着，少爷
That will be fine.  Hold on, young master.
No point hurrying.
这可是个重大的决定
Big decision, this.
让我们看看… 这个已经足够了
Let's have a look at-  This one is perfectly adequate.
我保证，一定让你完全满意
You will be utterly satisfied, I assure you.
依吉莉娅，你去准备一下
Egeria, go prepare yourself.
如果我们能把钱的问题先清一下…
If we might dispense with the pecuniary details...
呃？ 哦，好的
Oh, right.
你要什么价  一千
What's your price then?  1,000.
什么！？
Gerrae!
这个价我可以把纳波一半的妓女都睡了，再加上她们的老妈
I could have half the whores in Narbo for that, and their mothers.
我们可不是在纳波 我管你那是什么
We're not in Narbo, whatever that might be.
好吧，我的鸽子
All right, mydove.
我们给
We'll pay.
但那个女孩最好像特洛伊里的海伦一样使出她的看家本事伺候他
But the girl better fuck him like Helen of Troy with her ass on fire,
否则我要你好看
or I'll know the reason why.
说话  格涅乌斯·庞贝·麦格纳斯送来他的问候
Speak.  Gnaeus Pompey Magnus sends greetings.
希望你在他的房子里住的还满意
He hopes you find his house satisfactory.
马马虎虎
It'll do.
说他的重点  他的重点
Get to his point.  His point.
恺撒注定要失败的，而你和他一起
Caesar is doomed and you with him,
除非你庞贝单独讲和  还有呢？
unless you make a separate peace.  And?
如果你这样做，庞贝就对你手下留情，不与你计较
If you do, Pompey will be merciful and generous.
怎么个留情法？
How?
他会留你的性命，再给你一个省
He will give you your life. A province.
和足够的钱来保证你的尊严
Money enough to preserve your dignity.
是什么让他觉得我会把我自己的性命看得这么值钱？
What makes him think I value my life so high?
那你为什么还没有去希腊呢？
Why have you not left for Greece?
别跟我笑
Do not smile at me.
明天再来，到时我会给庞贝一个答复
Return tomorrow. I will give Pompey his answer then.
不是那边
Not that way.
别让人看见你
And disguiseyourself.
下去吧
Dismissed.
你把衣服脱下来？
You take clothes down?
你的口音真好笑
That's an interesting accent.
不懂
No understand.
哪里…
Where--
你从哪里来？
are you from?
哦，哪里来的
Oh. Where from.
不知道
Don't know.
你不知道自己是哪里人？
You don't know where you're from?
罗马很小就把我带走了
Rome take me very young.
杀了妈妈，爸爸，弟弟
Kill mother, father, brother,
把我带走了
take me.
哦，我明白了，可怜
Oh. I see. Sad.
你背过去，行吗？
Turn over, would you?
趴到床上
On your hands and knees.
Ah!
这地方不错
Nice place, this.
干净
Clean.
我想我没有
I don't suppose,
这个资格在这儿…
seeing as I'm with the quality...
一点也没有
Not a chance.
不，不，来真的，真打
No no no. No, do it for real. Fight.
哦，来呀，真打，该死的，打！
Oh, come on, fight, damn you! Fight!
这样好多了！
That's better!
嗯，好
Mmm, good.
好啊，辛西娅，精彩！
Brava, Cynthia! Brava!
哦，傻丫头，这不过是点擦伤
Oh, don't be so silly, it's just a scratch now.
没事，没事
There there.
波斯卡，到底什么事？
Yes, Posca, what is it?
我是来提醒你，你和优利亚家的阿提娅约好今晚共进晚餐
I am to remind you of your dinner tonight with Atia of the Julii.
他妈的！
Sons of Dis.
走吧
Now, run along.
他在哪？他到哪去了？
Where is he? Where can he be?
大忙人，他要搞政治
Busy man. Politics.
政治？他答应过我要来的
Politics? He promised he would come.
卡斯特！
Castor!
派人到庞贝，
Send a man to Pompey's--
我是说，马克·安东尼的住所，询问他的下落
I mean, Mark Antony's villa and enquire his whereabouts.
安东尼的下落，立刻就去，夫人
Antony's whereabouts, immediately, domina.
别说是我派人问的
Do not say it is I who sends to ask.
不是你派人去问的
Not you sends to ask.
慢着，他肯定会知道是我问的
Stay. He'll know it is I who asked.
不用派人了
Send no one.
我不派人了
I will send no one.
如果他来就来了，我才不在乎
If he comes, he comes, I don't care!
Halt!
欢迎驾到，老爷
Welcome, dominus.
抱歉迟到得太晚了，公事没完没了
Sorry to be so horribly late. Endless business.
你原谅我吗？ 当然
Will you forgive me?  Of course.
老实说，我几乎都不记得你要来了
I confess, I had quite forgotten you were coming.
这还真是个意外的惊喜
So this is a lovely surprise.
失陪一下，我去换件像样的衣服
Excuse me a moment, I will go and dress correctly.
他出来了
Mmm. Here he is,
小太阳神
young Apollo!
怎么样？
How was it?  It was pleasant.
很愉快
愉快？我就说了
Pleasant? I should say so.
他怎么样？ 像头牛
How was he?  Like bull.
怎么了？       没什么
What's wrong?   Nothing.
告诉我
Tell me.
马克·安东尼不打算到希腊去援助恺撒
Mark Antony does not intend to go to Greece to help Caesar.
我发誓效忠了一个不讲信义的人
I have sworn loyalty to a man of no honor.
至少这样你就不用去希腊了啊
Well you don't have to go to Greece then.
我们就可以在一起了  是的，但还是
We'll be together.  It's true, but still.
你不总说恺撒做的事不对吗？
Haven't you always said Caesar's cause is wrong?
这个不是重点
That is not the point.
这关系到道德原则
There is a moral principle involved.
你真是个傻瓜
What an idiot you are!
你不饿？
Not hungry?
哦，在军队里喝了这么多年的稀粥，我现在很容易就满足了
Oh, after so many years of soldier's porridge, I am easily sated.
看来这从希腊来的最新消息
Well, this last news from Greece
也没能给你增加点食欲
cannot have improved your appetite.
没有
Hardly.
真有这么糟吗？恺撒总能找到赢的办法
And is it really so bad? Caesar always finds a way to win.
庞贝的人马是恺撒的十倍
Pompey has gathered 10 men for every one of Caesar's.
这数字是不讲情面的
Arithmetic has no mercy.
我也担心是这样
I'd feared it was so.
那你打算怎么办？
What do you intend to do then?
我不知道
I don't know.
你已经是一个有权势的人了，人民也爱戴你
You've become a powerful man. The people love you.
这不过是因为他们不了解我
Only because they don't know me.
要是你愿意，你可以成为罗马的第一人
You could be the first man in Rome, if you wanted.
我从没这么想过
I hadn't thought about it like that.
那你应该…
Well, you should.
你该好好想想
You should think about that.
我在想一些截然不同的东西
I'm thinking about something entirely different.
Mmm.
水
Water.
我能睡上一个星期
I could sleep for a week.
我在想
I've been thinking.
我们应该结婚
We should get married.
结婚？
Married?
我们为什么想要这么做？
Why should we want to do that of all things?
也许因为我爱你
Perhaps I love you.  Ah.
你在开玩笑
You're joking.
有那么一下，你还真吓着我了
For a moment there you had me worried.
我不是在跟你开玩笑
I am not joking with you.
哦，我亲爱的女人哪！
Oh, my dear woman.
别担心
Please don't worry,
我不是想跟你装温柔
I'm not going soft on you.
我是从战略上考虑
I'm thinking strategically.
如果恺撒战败了
If Caesar is defeated,
我不可能和庞贝一党结成良好的同盟
I can't very well form an alliance with the Pompeians.
我需要保护  对
I need protection.  True.
这有我什么事？
What's in it for me?
如果恺撒战败了…
If Caesar is defeated--
那我也同样战败了
Then I will be defeated also.
除非你到希腊去加入他
Only if you join him in Greece.
但如果你留在罗马
But if you stay in Rome,
你将会有很好地位
you will be very well situated.
人民站在你一边
You have the people with you,
这个城市也是属于你的
you have possession of the city.
你缺的只是钱
You only lack money.
同时人们也非常尊敬你的名字…
And whilst your name is perfectly respectable--
我不是贵族  正是
I am no patrician.  Exactly.
可是一旦和我的家族结合，你就既有了钱，也有了贵族身份
But allied with my house, you would have both coin and nobility
要是你愿意，你还可以称王
to make yourself king if you wished it so.
而你就是王后
And you would be queen.
我会是爱你的，顺从你的妻子
I would be your loving and obedient wife.
只要我愿意背弃一个朋友
If only I were willing to desert a friend.
一个和你同血缘的人
A man of your own blood.
哦，你太高尚了，这不适合你，是吗？  我希望我表面上是的
Oh, too honorable for that, are you?  I like to appear so.
可我不认为你会为了面子而死
But I don't think you'll die for the sake of appearances.
我不会吗？ 恺撒不管怎么样都会死的
Will I not?  Caesar will die in any case.
但你很聪明，不会无端端地陪他去送死的
But you are far too clever to share his fate needlessly.
我知道现在才意识到…
I had not realized until now...
你原来是个多么邪恶的老女妖啊！
what a wicked old harpy you really are.
滚出去！
Get out!
给我滚！
谢谢你，波罗
Thank you, Pullo.
立正！
Atattention!
Ow.
大白天的能在床上躺着，多奢侈啊
Abed in daylight, what luxury.
不道德吗？
Wickedness.
父亲，那个侏儒来找你
Father, that dwarf is asking for you.
马克·安东尼阁下
Excellency Mark Antony
下令13军团在到战神之地去集合
orders 13th Legion to muster on the Field of Mars.
为什么？我们要上哪儿去？ 希腊
Why? Where are we going?  Greece.
护民官！
Tribune!
我应该怎么答复庞贝？
What shall I tell Pompey?  Oh!
当然
Of course.
对不起，我把你给忘了
Excuse me. I had forgot you.
他的皮肤有点干燥
His skin is a little dry.
把他送出去之前，好好给他上点油
Have him well-oiled before he is presented.
哦，天哪！
Bona dea.
我怕这个是…？  给赛维莉娅的礼物
I am afraid to ask.  Gifts for Servilia.
你真帅，让我好好看看
How fine you look. Let me see.
我太为你骄傲了，你终于成了一个真正的男人了
I am so proud of you. You're a real man at last, eh?
我们为什么要给赛维莉娅送礼？
Why are we giving gifts to Servilia?
那只老乌鸦和卡托，还有其他人关系挺好
The old crow stands in well with Cato and the rest.
当恺撒和他的走狗马克·安东尼战败的时候…
When Caesar and his dog Antony are defeated--
如果他们会失败的话
If they are defeated.
当他们失败的时候  我们得要让她帮忙说好话
When they are defeated, we'll need her good will.
而你认为送这个可以收买她？ 我没觉得有什么不行
And this will buy it, you think?  I do not see why not.
又粗又长的玩意总是受欢迎的
A large penis is always welcome.
你觉得这还不够吗？ 在你对她做了的那些事情之后？
You think it's not enough?  After what you did to her?
我做什么了？我对她做了什么了？ 别装蒜了，我又不傻
What I did? What did I do to her?  Please! I'm not stupid.
是你搞的让恺撒和她断绝关系的
It was you made Caesar renounce her.
就算是我做的，她又不知道  她会不知道？
What if I did? She doesn't know it.  Does she not?
她也不傻啊  赛维莉亚人从不耍手段
She's not stupid either.  Servilia has no guile in her.
如果她知道了，我们肯定会听说的
If she knows it, we would certainly have heard about it.
你自己最清楚了，我肯定
You know best, I'm sure.
无论如何，我们要把这份礼给她
In any case, you will take the gifts to her
看她是怎么想的
and see what she's thinking.
她一直很喜欢你
She's always been very fond of you.
而你要到米狄欧兰侬（米兰）去
And you will go to Mediolanum.
泰门会送你去  米狄欧兰侬？
Timon will take you.  Mediolanum?
是，他们在那儿有个很好的学院
Yes, they have a very good academy there.
我不明白  你是个男人了
I don't understand.  You're a man now.
对优利亚家的男人来说罗马不再是个安全的地方
Rome's not safe for men of the Julii.
他的脚趾甲太难看了
His toenails are ugly.
让他们给他修剪一下，再上色，再给他头上戴点花
Have them cut and painted and put some flowers on his head.
哦，送点冰过来，六桶吧
Oh, and send over some ice. Six barrels, say.
六桶冰
Six barrels of ice.
别傻看着
Well, don't look so foolish.
我知道我在干什么
I know what I'm about.
你母亲太客气了
Your mother's too kind.
她送这么大方的礼，是要我用什么来还？
To what do I owe this generosity?
这只一种出于友谊的表示
It's a gesture of friendship.
友谊
Friendship.
谢谢你母亲的…友谊
Thank your mother for her... friendship.
我希望有一天我能报答她的…
I hope one day to reciprocate her...
友谊
friendship.
那我走了
I will go then.
对不起
Excuse me.
等等
Wait.
请原谅我的坏脾气
Please, forgive my ill humor.
没什么要原谅的
There's nothing to forgive.
你还是个小女孩的时候我就认识你了，你有一颗善良的心灵
I have known you since you were a little girl. You have a good soul.
我知道不管别人做了什么
I know that whatever others might do,
你是无辜的
you are blameless.
这点我明白
I know that.
我…我没有做，那是，我不能…
I- I do not- that is, I cannot--
嘘，嘘
Shh shh shh shh.
没关系，不用解释了
It's all right. There's no need.
告诉你妈妈
Tell your mother
我很感谢她的礼物
that I am grateful for the gifts
我还是一如既往的珍惜和她的友谊
and that I treasure her friendship as always.
你一定要再来看我，好吗？
You must come and visit me again. Will you?
我会的  你保证？
I will.  Promise?
我希望我们俩之间没有反感
I want there to be no ill feeling between us.
我保证
I promise.
你作个好女孩
You be a good girl.
要听话
Do as you're told.
我在外面等你
I'll wait for you outside.
Shh shh shh.
愿战争女神保佑你
Bellona protect you.
神后也保佑你
And Juno keep you.
一支舰队已经出发驶向希腊
A fleet of ships has set sail for Greece
它满载着马克·安东尼将军的军队
carrying the army of General Mark Antony.
这个月的公共面包
This month's public bread
是由卡比托奈山的兄弟磨坊提供的
is provided by the Capitoline Brotherhood of Millers.
兄弟磨坊只用最精良的面粉
The Brotherhood uses only the finest flour.
制作纯正的罗马面包
True Roman bread,
给真正的罗马人
for true Romans.
大难临头了，我全身都湿透了
This is cac, this is! I'm wet through.
我们安全的很！
We're perfectly safe.
已经向海神敬献过了丰厚的贡品
A very good offering was made to Triton!
如果海神不能把我身上弄干点儿，那就见他的鬼去吧
If Triton can't keep me drier than this, he can suck my cock!
你怎么学不会闭上你的臭嘴
Why can't you learn to keep your fat mouth shut?!
翻译:TLF字幕组